Guide to the Autograph Manuscript collection ARC.206
Brooklyn Historical Society
- Paulding, James Kirke, ND [1839?], 1839; 1974.011 folder 79; 4674; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 74)
  ND [1839?] letter, from Secretary of the Navy James Kirke Paulding, at Washington, DC, to James Herring of the Apollo Gallery, New York City, re: invitation extended to Paulding, mentions Mr. Clark; 1839 informal letter, from Secretary Paulding, at Washington, DC, to John Howard Payne, at New York City, re: Payne's "business"
- Peale, Rembrandt, ND [1835], 1859; 1974.011 folder 80; 4675; 2 items (Box 1, Folder 75)
  1835 circular, printed at New York City, advertising "Peale's Graphics, A Manual of Drawing and Writing, for the use of Schools and Families," with ND note, from Rembrandt Peale, at New York City, to Professor Griscom, re: soliciting Griscom's opinion of the manual; 1859 letter, from Rembrandt Peale, at Philadelphia, to James Carson Brevoort, at Brooklyn, re: Brevoort's "valuable painting," mentions photograph and engraving used for comparison, "Putnam" as subject, Hall the engraver, Pine and Wright, painters, and the Francis Hopkinson family
- Pickens, Francis Wilkinson, 1843; 1974.011 folder 81; 4676; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 76)
  1843 letter, from South Carolina Congressman Francis Wilkinson Pickens, to John L. O'Sullivan of the Democratic Review, at New York City, re: subscription, and interest in the "late number containing the likeness of Mr. Calhoun"
- Pierpont, John, 1844; 1974.011 folder 82; 4677; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 77)
  1844 letter, from John Pierpont, at Boston, to Messrs. Geo. F. Cooledge Bros. [the address missing, but the identification made in the LIHS card catalog record], at New York, re: pre-press corrections
- Polk, James K., 1843; 1974.011 folder 83; 4678; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 78)
  1843, letter from Tennessee Governor and future President of the United States, James K. Polk, at Columbia, Tennessee, to Messrs. J. and Henry G. Langley, publishers of The United States Magazine & Democratic Review, at New York, re: subscription
- Potter, Henry Codman, 1882; 1974.011 folder 84; 4679; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 79)
  1882 letter, from Henry Codman Potter, at Grace Church Rectory, New York, to an unknown addressee, re: forwarding substance of Potter's remarks at an anniversary
- Prud'Homme, John Francis Eugene, 1852; 1974.011 folder 85; 4680; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 80)
  1852 letter, from John Francis Eugene Prud'Homme, to the Brooklyn daguerreotypist Gabriel Harrison, re: praising Harrison's work
- Pynchon, Joseph, 1782; 1974.011 folder 86; 4681; 1 item (Box 1, Folder 81)
  1782 letter, from Joseph Pynchon, at New York, to Jared Landon, at Southold, LI, re: requesting Landon's help in hosting Pynchon's daughter Sally, prior to her trip to Guilford in the care of Landon's brother, David, for the purpose of attending to her share of the estate of "the late Mr. Ruggles," mentions the family of Mr. Brown at Guilford and of the late William Hubbard at Southold
- Raymond, Henry Jarvis, 1974.011 folder 87; 4682; 1 item (Box 2, Folder 82)
  ND note, from Henry Jarvis Raymond to Alden J. Spooner, re: reference to a transcript of Raymond's earlier remarks
- Rhett, Robert Barnwell, 1841; 1974.011 folder 88; 4683; 1 item (Box 2, Folder 83)
  1841 letter, from Robert Barnwell Rhett, at Georgetown, the the Editors of the Democratic Review, re: subscription
- Saltonstall, Rosewell, 1838; 1974.011 folder 90; 4684; 1 item (Box 2, Folder 84)
  1838 letter, from Rosewell Saltonstall, at New York City, to John Smalley, [Brooklyn], re: requesting publication of an enclosed note, refuting claims for a new system of navigation made before the Navy Board by John Hale Sheerwood, the not being dedicated to Commodore Ridgeway
- Schuyler, Peter et al., 1720; 1974.001 folder 22; 4635; 1 item (Box 2, Folder 85)
  1720 unsigned and unsealed articles of agreement, an apparent draft copy of a contract to be made between Peter Schuyler, of Albany, and Ebenezer Willson and Peter Fauconnier, of New York City, re: the disposition of "a Tract of Land in Albany and Dutchess County, called Westenhook," refers to an Act of Assembly of the Province of New York "for the easier partition of Lands in Joint tenancy" and mentions that the covenanters have laid out nine lots "for the nine Patentees therein concerned," the lots having been surveyed and mapped by Philip Verplank
- Schuyler, Phillip, 1714-1716; 1974.001 folder 23; 4636; 6 items (Box 2, Folder 86)
  6 letters, all in Dutch, from Philip Schuyler, at New York, to Rutgert Bleeker, at Albany: 1714/1715 letter, re: provisions, mentions "de Twee Scheepers die van de Winter hier uyt Liverpool ingekoomen zyn"; 1714[/1715] letter, mentions Coenraad Ten Eyck, Gerrardus Beekman, Jacobus Van Dyck; 1715 letter, mentions ships and Mr. Delancy and Mr. Van Dam; 1715 letter, mentions Jan Van Nes, Jacob Visher, Capt. Mathys De Hart, Mr. Rackett (the latter, re: London); 1715 letter, mentions Frans Winne, Capt. Bassett [sic]; 1716 letter, mentions Cornelis Swits, Jan Van Nes and his brother Symon Van Nes
- Seward, William H., 1840, 1847; 1974.011 folder 91; 4685; 2 items (Box 2, Folder 87)
  1840 letter, from New York Governor William H. Seward, at Albany, to J. Griscom, LL.D., at West Haverford, Delaware Co., PA, re: receipt of "the proceedings of the National Convention for the promotion of popular education"; 1847 letter, from Seward, at Auburn, to Jno Griscom, M.D., re: etiquette for previous incumbents, with regard to new administrations, mentions "His Excellency the Governor" [A third Seward letter, dated 1868, to George Hannah of the Long Island Historical Society, has been removed, and placed with the Records of the Society, in folder #70 of that collection.] [See also: letters of William H. Seward in "Henry Onderdonk Jr. (1804-1886) Correspondence, 1835-18—", Box A0028-A, folder "S"]
- Shilell Jr., J.W., 1804; 1974.054; 4686; 1 item (Box 2, Folder 88)
- Simms, William Gilmore, ND [1845?]; 1974.011 folder 92; 4687; 1 item (Box 2, Folder 89)
  ND note, from William Gilmore Simms to Henry G. Langley Esq., re: Simms's biography, "The Life of Francis Marion" [Langley published the 5th ed., 1845]
- Smith, Robert, 1803; 1974.011 folder 93; 4688; 1 item (Box 2, Folder 90)
  1803 letter, from U.S. Secretary of the Navy Robert Smith to Rhode Island Senator Christopher Ellery, re: the promotion to Lieutenant of "Mr. Smith[,] Midshipman" from Rhode Island (no relation to the author)
- Smith, Seba, 1847, 1855; 1974.011 folder 94; 4689; 2 items (Box 2, Folder 91)
  1847 letter, from Seba Smith, at New York, to "Messrs. Gales & Seaton" (Robert Gales Jr. and Wiliam Winston Seaton), editors of the National Intelligencer, at Washington, DC, re: Smith proposes to write a column for Gales & Seaton's journal, offering a perspective on national affairs as seen from New York ("This great, bustling, noisy, restless city is a never failing fountain of material…"), includes a brief, informal resumé; 1855 letter, from Seba Smith, at New York, to Professor Jean Louis Rodolphe Agassiz, at Cambridge, re: Smith's essay on Agassiz in the United States Magazine
- Sparks, Jared, 1831, 1844, 1851, 1864; 1974.011 folder 95; 4690; 4 items (Box 2, Folder 92)
  1831 letter, from Jared Sparks to Professor John Griscom, re: enclosed autograph of George Washington [note: this letter may indicate the provenance of a George Washington autograph in the collections of the Brooklyn Historical Society, but the autograph has been separated and any such connection has not been determined at this time]; 1844 letter, from Jared Sparks, at Cambridge, to James Brown Esq., re: biographies, mentions Roger Williams, "President Dwight", "Pike", and Sparks's own "Life of Count Pulaski"; 1851 letter, from Jared Sparks, at Cambridge, to Charles Francis Adams (1807-1886), re: Adams's historical writings, extensively responding to Adams's citing of Sparks with regard to the legation of William Carmichael and William Short in Spain during the post-Revolutionary War period, quoting from Sparks' interviews with Short (with mention of Carmichael's "irregular" habits), and, separately, discussing "Conway's Cabal" (General Horatio Gates's effort to supersede George Washington) at length, referring to Sparks's visit with the Marquis de Lafayette at LaGrange in 1829 and elaborating on Sparks's opinion of the disposition of the French towards General Washington, mentioning Count Vergennes and Marshall de Maillebois; 1864 letter, from Jared Sparks, at Cambridge, to S. B. Noyes, Esq., re: the reception of Benjamin Franklin at the court of France, viz. a commemoration of the event by "the ladies of Brooklyn" [See also: letters of Jared Sparks in "Henry Onderdonk Jr. (1804-1886) Correspondence, 1835-18—", Box A0028-A, folder "Sparks, Jared"]
- Stark, John (General), 1781; 1974.001 folder 24; 4637; 1 item (Box 2, Folder 93)
  1781 wartime letter from General John Stark, at Saratoga, to Colonel Wallbridge, at Skeensborough, re: request for assistance in aiding Captain Hickok with transport of the General's flag to Canada, mentions the prior day's capture by local militia of five Tories from Canada who held orders "of a similar nature to those taken at Bennington"
- Stuyvesant, Peter, 1656; 1974.054; 4691; 1 item (Box 2, Folder 94)
- Tallmadge, Benjamin, 1782; 1974.011 folder 96; 4692; 1 item (Box 2, Folder 95)
  1782 letter, from Colonel Benjamin Tallmadge, at Bedford, to the Honorable William Smith, Esq., at Goshen, re: the reinstatement of "Mr. Booth," and the role of commanding officers in granting "certificates" to troops for services rendered "in similar situations," mentions the "Commander in Chief" [George Washington]
- Thomas, Francis, 1843; 1974.011 folder 97; 4693; 1 item (Box 2, Folder 96)
  1843 letter, from Maryland Governor Francis Thomas, at Annapolis, the the Editors of the Democratic Review, at Washington, re: cancellation of subscription
- Thompson, Benjamin Franklin, 1848-1849, c.1930; 1974.001 folder 25; 4638; 10 items (Box 2, Folder 97)
  5 jovial letters from Benjamin F. Thompson, at Hempstead, LI, to his cousin Anna Matilda Woodhull, mostly at Freehold, NJ, re: Thompson's writing of the Woodhull genealogy, etc., with typescript copies of same [unchecked for accuracy, JM 4.14.2005] made at time of accession to the Long Island Historical Society: 1848 letter, re: Woodhull's recent visit with Thompson, inferences to her social life, and appreciation for her help with his researches, mentions the Woodman family, a Mr. Mills of Morristown, Dr. Silas L. Condict, Rev. Zachariah Greene of Brookhaven, LI; 1848 letter, mentions Dr. Lewis Condict of Morristown and son Nathan Woodhull Condict, Gov. Dickerson, Messrs. Hicks & Willis (teachers), Edward and Jacob Vanderhoof; 1848 letter, mentions Rev. Mr. Condict of Newark, Dr. Lewis Condict, James Woodhull, William Woodhull, John & Frances (Satterly) Woodhull, Selah S. Woodhull, Elizabeth Woodhull Griswold, and Thompson's trip through western New York State to Niagara; 1849 letter, mentions Henry Woodhull,General Woodhull, a Broadway production of C. Edwards Lester to be called "Kate Woodhull", Rev. Richard Woodhull of Thomaston, ME, Samuel Woodhull of Utica, NY, Mary Woodhull Lacy of Lockport, Woodhulls of Oneida Co., NY, Stephen Woodhull of Setauket, LI, Abraham Cooper Woodhull, and a Mrs. Ellet; 1849 letter, mentions many of the above figures, California Gold Rush, Albert Woodhull of Woodhull & Minturn, Thomas Cooper, John Cooper
- Tomlinson, Jabrey H., 1836; 1974.011 folder 98; 4694; 1 item (Box 2, Folder 98)
  1836 letter, from Jabrey H. Tomlinson, at Stratford, to Hon. Victory Birdseye, at Pompey, Onondaga Co., NY, re: "papers" sent to Birdseye
- Tompkins, Daniel D., 1809; 1974.011 folder 99; 4695; 1 item (Box 2, Folder 99)
  1809 letter, from New York Governor Daniel D. Tompkins, at Albany, to Major Jno. Vernon, re: request, viz. the artillery company, at Albany, mentions Captain John Mills
- Truxtun, Thomas, 1792; 1974.011 folder 100; 4696; 1 item (Box 2, Folder 100)
  1792 letter, from Captain Thomas Truxtun, at London, to Messrs. John Warder & Co., re: order for the ship Delaware, concluded by Truxtun and Mr. Constable, referring to East India Investment, mentions specie and merchandise, Truxtun's travel to Madras and Bengal, desire to examine a muster of iron prior to purchase "for the people of India make a great difference in this article"
- Van Buren, Martin, ND; 1974.011 folder 101; 4697; 1 item (Box 2, Folder 101)
  ND note, in the third-person, from Martin Van Buren to John Wells Esq., re: dinner invitation (with photocopy)
- Van Ness, William Peter, 1819; 1974.011 folder 102; 4698; 1 item (Box 2, Folder 102)
  1819 letter, from William Peter Van Ness, at Kinderhook, to John Wells Esq., at Albany, re: adjournment of the District Court
- Walker, Robert John, 1842; 1974.011 folder 103; 4699; 1 item (Box 2, Folder 103)
  1842 letter, from Robert John Walker, at Washington, DC, to Messrs. J. & Henry G. Langley, at New York, re: remittance
- Washington, George, 1780; 1974.001 folder 26; 4639; 1 item (Box 2, Folder 104)
  1780 wartime letter from General George Washington, at Morristown, NJ, to Major General Greene, re: securing the means of conveying intelligence between Washington's Headquarters at Morristown and Rhode Island where the French fleet and army are expected to arrive, and also mentions need for the requisition of horses for the army at Morristown
- Washington, George & Colonel Trumbull, 1783; 1974.054; 4700; 1 item (Box 2, Folder 105)
- Wesley, John, 1777; 1974.011; 14609; 2 items (Box 2, Folder 105a)
- Whittier, John Greenleaf, ND; 1974.011 folder 106; 4701; 1 item (Box 2, Folder 106)
  ND note, from John Greenleaf Whittier to an unknown addressee ["Dear fd," i.e., a fellow Quaker], re: a book, mentions Labadist preachers
- Wolcott, Oliver, 1796; 1974.011 folder 107; 4702; 1 item (Box 2, Folder 107)
  1796 letter, from Oliver Wolcott, at the Treasury Department, to Matthew Clarkson Esq., Commisioner of Loans, at New York, re: a remittance from the United States Treasurer for $90,000
- Woodbury, Levi, 1843; 1974.011 folder 108; 4703; 2 items (Box 2, Folder 108)
  1843 letter, from former New Hampshire Governor and former Secretary of the Navy and the Treasury, Levi Woodbury, at Washington, DC, to John O'Sullivan, at New York City, re: Woodbury's engraved portrait; 1843 letter, from Levi Woodbury, at Portsmouth, NH, to Messrs. J. & Henry G. Langley, at New York City, re: offering to submit material for the Democratic Review
- Woodford, William (Colonel), 1776; 1974.001 folder 27; 4640; 1 item (Box 2, Folder 109)
  1776 wartime letter from Colonel William Woodford, at Kemp's Landing, to Captain Jonathan Clark, at Ferry Point, re: transport of prisoners (where is Ferry Point? May be in scope)
- Woodhull, Nathaniel (General), 1775; 1974.001 folder 28; 4704; 1 item (Box 2, Folder 110)
  1775 Commission of Joseph Harris, as Ensign in the 2nd Company of Foot in the Militia in Charlotte Precinct, Dutchess County, NY, signed by General Nathaniel Woodhull, printed matter [the signature and seal of Woodhull are missing from the document ]
- Woodhull, Nathaniel, 1776; 1974.054; 4705; 1 item (Box 2, Folder 111)
- Wright, Silas Jr., 1832, 1841, 1843; 1974.011 folder 110; 4707; 3 items (Box 2, Folder 113)
  1832 letter, from New York State Comptroller Silas Wright Jr., at Albany, to the Treasurer of the Pompey Academy of Onondaga county, NY, re: State funds due the Academy; 1841 letter from U. S. Senator Silas Wright Jr., at Washington, DC, to Hon. John O'Sullivan, at New York City, re: subscriptions to the Democratic Review for Wright and for John Leslie Russell of Canton, St. Lawrence county, NY; 1843 note, from Silas Wright Jr. to the Publishers of the Democratic Review, re: forwarding a submission from an unnamed poet to the Review
- [unknown] British legal documents, 1627, [1677]; 1974.011 folder 111; 4708; 2 items (Box 2, Folder 114)
  2 17th Century legal documents, probably copies, in antique script, with 1889 note of provenance, signed by John M. Burt, an insurer, of New York City, addressed "To the Librarian": 1627 petition, from [Lionel Cranfield] the Earl of Middlesex, to King Charles I, re: a dispute between the Earl of Middlesex and the Earl of Desmond, mentions Virginia; [1677] petition, by unknown person or persons, to King Charles II, re: a loan [? Appears to be an early copy.]